<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The whole art of converse containing necessary instructions for all persons, of what quality and condition soever : with the characters of the four humours of the English and French, as to their way of conversing / by D.A., Gent.</title>
            <author>D. A.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26035</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11160</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11822010</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11822010</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49595</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26035)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49595)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 45:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The whole art of converse containing necessary instructions for all persons, of what quality and condition soever : with the characters of the four humours of the English and French, as to their way of conversing / by D.A., Gent.</title>
                  <author>D. A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 128 [i.e. 130] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Joseph Hindmarsh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First ed. Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conversation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49595:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49595:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE WHOLE ART OF CONVERSE: <hi>CONTAINING</hi> Neceſſary inſtructions for all Perſons, of what Quality, and Condition ſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WITH</hi> The Characters of the four Humours, of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> as to their way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing.</p>
            <p>By <hi>D. A.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Joſeph Hindmarſh,</hi> Bookſeller to His Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Highneſs, at the Sign of the <hi>Black-Bull</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> near the <hi>Exchange.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:49595:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49595:2"/>
            <head>THE Moſt material CONTENTS <hi>OF THIS</hi> BOOK.</head>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>ARTICLE. I.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. WHat this Art is, and its different Branches.</item>
                  <item>2. In what Senſe a civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe is taken here.</item>
                  <item>3. That Pride is deſtructive to Civility.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49595:3"/>
                  <item>4. That 'tis rudeneſs to ſpeak ill of our Neighbours in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</item>
                  <item>5. 'Tis rudeneſs to be too talkative in Converſation.</item>
                  <item>6. That anger is againſt the Laws of a civil Converſe.</item>
                  <item>7. Obſtinacy is contrary to the Laws of Civility.</item>
                  <item>8. 'Tis inconſiſtent with Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility to force Drink on a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or any other in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</item>
                  <item>9. To ſpeak too high is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Laws of a civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe.</item>
                  <item>10. That frequent Oaths are inconſiſtent with Civility.</item>
                  <item>11. When Railery is conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent, and when inconſiſtent with Civility.</item>
                  <item>12. That exceſſive Flattery is a great rudeneſs.</item>
                  <item>13. How we may ſhun
<pb facs="tcp:49595:3"/> Flattery, and Criticiſm.</item>
                  <item>14. That we ought to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our Diſcourſe to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, and Capacity of thoſe we Converſe.</item>
                  <item>15. That 'tis a duty of Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to Converſe ſometimes with our Friends by Letters.</item>
                  <item>16. That all Jeſt or Earneſt tending to Impiety, is an extream rudeneſs.</item>
                  <item>17. That 'tis an extream rudeneſs to ſpeak to the diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of any Nation in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Natives.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>ARTICIE. II.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. OF the familiar Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</item>
                  <item>2. Of the Learned Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</item>
                  <item>3. Of the Intereſs'd Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:49595:4"/>
                  <item>4. The Character of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine Humour.</item>
                  <item>5. The Character of the Cholerick.</item>
                  <item>6. The Character of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy Humour.</item>
                  <item>7. The Character of the Phlegmatick.</item>
                  <item>8. The Character of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as to their way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing.</item>
                  <item>9. The Character of the <hi>French,</hi> as to their way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA,</head>
            <p>Page 33. laſt line, read inbred. Page 38. laſt line, read Immoral.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49595:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> Whole ART of <hi>CONVERSE.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTION. I.</hi> What this ART is.</head>
               <p>A Moderate care of a good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute is laudable, as being commended to us by the Holy Writings, and a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ambition to conquer the Hearts of ſuch as we are ordinarily conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with, is a rational, and lawful ſort of Self-love; but neither of theſe we ſhall ever attain to, unleſs we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand perfectly the Art of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, and how to practiſe exactly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49595:5"/> its Precepts in every particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture. Hence we may eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture the Nature, or the Eſſence and End of this Art; for if you mind to play the <hi>Logician,</hi> and give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate definition thereof, you may call it a habit, teaching us how to demean our ſelves with our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, in order to gain their Love and Eeem, which two things have ſuch a dependency the one of the other, that they go commonly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: whether it be, that Eſteem is the ſource of Love, or Love, which I am more apt to believe, cauſeth us to contemplate the beloved Object in ſuch a byaſs as we magnifie in our corrupted judgments, its leaſt perfections.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49595:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> In what ſence a civil Converſe is taken here.</head>
               <p>A Civil Converſation may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken either as related to our Actions, or to our Diſcourſe; in the firſt ſence 'tis a certain accurateneſs and decency in all our Actions, or in our outward Behaviour. I intend to ſpeak little or nothing of this kind of Civility. 1. Becauſe there is a <hi>French Treatiſe</hi> Engliſhed on the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, accurate and particular enough; which, though it regards more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the <hi>French</hi> cuſtoms, may eaſily be adapted to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Humour and Civility, now not much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the <hi>French.</hi> 2. Becauſe I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hought it alwaies ſuperfluous, or at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſt of little uſe, to preſcribe Rules or Ceremonies, that change not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> every Age, but almoſt every Year.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49595:6"/>
'Tis then beſt for every one as to this part, to obſerve and follow the cuſtoms of his own Country, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they be not intirely barbarous, and repugnant to the known practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Civility of theſe Nations that are commonly accounted Civil; as <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> ever were, and all <hi>Great Britain, England</hi> I mean, and <hi>Scotland,</hi> undoubtedly now are.</p>
               <p>If we take a civil Converſation, as related not to Mens Actions, but to their Diſcourſe, by the general Notion given above of the Art of Converſing; we ſhall ſay 'tis a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain exactneſs in all our words and expreſſions, in order to gain, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, or encreaſe the eſteem and friendſhip of thoſe we Converſe with: The Rules then we muſt ſquare our Actions by in a civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, are unchangeable, and neithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> confin'd to time nor place, but ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all of all Ages, and of a good reliſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with all Nations, as being grounde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49595:6"/> on common Senſe, not on Mens changeable Fancies. Theſe are but two, and eaſie to be retain'd: The firſt is, to ſay nothing that may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the Eſteem and Love Men have for us: The ſecond is, to ſpeak ſuch things as may contribute to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the encreaſe of both: how, and with what accuracy we are to obſerue theſe Precepts, the enſuing <hi>Section</hi> ſhall declare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi> That Pride is deſtructive to Civility.</head>
               <p>A Civil Converſe, as I have ſaid above, is a certain exactneſs in all our words and expreſſions, in or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der to gain, conſerve, or encreaſe the Eſteem and Friendſhip of thoſe we converſe withal; that nothing is more deſtructive to it than Pride, every one underſtands, that knows
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49595:7"/> contraries to be inconſiſtent toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that Civility is nothing elſe, if well reflected on, but a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectuous Humility.</p>
               <p>I mean not here that inward Pride which we are neither concern'd with nor to judge of, but that outward and proud Behaviour, either in Geſts or Speech, whereby thoſe we ſpeak to, underſtand we are wiſe in ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own conceit, though perhaps ſimple and vain Fools in their thoughts Perſons of Quality betray them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to a ſecret contempt of thoſe they ſpeak to, if they preſume too much upon their Nobility, or ſeem to ſlight others on this account only that they are (as they ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in <hi>Scotland</hi>) but bare Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               <p>'Tis a rudeneſs ſcarce pardonable eſpecially before perſons we are not acquainted with, to run out in the praiſe of our Anceſtors, for that would be too viſible a vanity, and a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49595:7"/> too affected deſire of Honour. Some are ſo extravagant in this Point, as to entertain Strangers with nothing elſe but long Deſcriptions of their own Pedigree, and Grandure of their fore-Runners, true or falſe. I ſay true or falſe, becauſe I have known ſeveral in Forraign Countries, and I wiſh none of my own Country-men may be guilty of this inſufferable vanity; who, though they were in extream miſery, pretended to be Couſin <hi>Germans,</hi> or near Relations to the greateſt Noble-men of <hi>Scotland,</hi> upon this account only, That they were either <hi>Hamiltons, Douglaſſes, Gordons, Seatons, Maxuelles,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Perſons of Quality wrong them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more than they are aware of, when they rail ſo violently againſt diſproportionate Alliances; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, though I grant they may have reaſon when the diſproportion is too great, or the quality not recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the quantity, yet, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49595:8"/> they are guilty of an extream rudeneſs, by diſcovering thus in a familiar Converſe, what they call a Noble Spirit, and others of as ſound Senſe, think and call an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-Chriſtian</hi> Pride; which is as yet more inſufferable in ſuch, as by their Birth can pretend no advantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their Neighbours. If ſuch make appear this paſſion to be their predominant amongſt their equals, or before their ſuperiours, they loſe without doubt the Eſteem of thoſe, and the Love of theſe, and are whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incapable of all civil Converſe: whoſe limits we ſtill out-go, to ſpeak generally whenſoever we ſay any thing tending directly or indirectly, to the diſcovery of our Secret Pride; as thoſe do, who boaſt perpetually of their Warlike Exploits, with as great confidence, as if the Hearers judged them not to be Liars: and if they were put to it, extraordinary Cowards.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49595:8"/>
               <p>Others do out-weary your Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with a number of innumerable idle Circumſtances of their Affairs, or their Suits in Law: How they have put a trick upon this Man, by what means they have engaged that other in their Intereſt: and if they had not been very active in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, all had been gon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And when they have ſpent half an Hour, and all your Patience, in ſaying the ſame thing, with theſe idle Repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>quoth he, and quoth ſhe,</hi> they ſhall begin immediately the ſame Story to the firſt that comes in, without giving them ſo much time as to edge in a word.</p>
               <p>Others will trouble the whole company with a long <hi>Panegyrick</hi> of their good conduct in the guidance of their <hi>Domeſtick</hi> Affairs: they will give you an exact Account of the ſplendour of their Table, of their ordinary and extraordinary Expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of their Alms and Liberalities,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49595:9"/> and of their leaſt Concerns, if they hope by ſuch petty Narratives, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your Eſteem or Applauſe. 'Tis odds to be in the company of ſome Women, but they will run out in the praiſe of their Children, and lull you aſleep with the petty Dialogues they have dayly together. I was acquainted with a Gentlewoman in the South of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who was a burden to the whole Country ſhe lived in upon this account: Her firſt Complement in her viſits to her Friends, was alwaies, <hi>If they had not ſeen her fine, her lovely, her unparallel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Boy?</hi> She was ſo Complaiſant, as never to change this diſcourſe, whatever byaſs ye had taken to be rid of it; If ſhe had been interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a moment, that ſhe might fetch her breath, ſhe would inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commence again her firſt unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Tune, and inform you of all the motions of her fine Boy; How he weep'd, how he laugh'd, how he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49595:9"/> mov'd his feet, his eyes, and his hands, how he utter'd to her in half words, his young and tender Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections.</p>
               <p>Some again will force you <hi>Will</hi> ye <hi>Nill</hi> ye, to make an undeſerv'd <hi>Elogium</hi> of their Children by their own good example: They are not (ſay they) like others, God be bleſs'd, they are Father-like, ſharp, witty, and pretty, hopeful, and what not? as if you did take as much pleaſure in hearing theſe little Tales, as they to tell them. Let theſe, and the like defects, true Off-ſprings of Pride, be diligently ſhun'd, by all ſuch as pretend to be accounted civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49595:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> That 'tis rudeneſs to ſpeak ill of our Neighbours in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</head>
               <p>SOme have ſo little judgment, as to imagine they cannot Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh their own Repute upon a ſurer ground, than on the Ruine of their Neighbours good-Name; they call all the World (themſelves only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) Fools, and on this account, they would be lookt upon as Wits, or Stars of the firſt Magnitude. Such Men are moſt of all uncivil; they may be perhaps admir'd, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd by the undiſcerning ſort, and ſuch as are as unprovided of ſound Senſe, and true Wit, as themſelves: but they ſhall never pleaſe ſolid judgments, and ſuch as have both Science to diſcern what is praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, and Conſcience, not to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49595:10"/> through envy, the Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments either of Art, or Nature, they ſee in others, and cannot attain to If you ſay to Men of this temper, ſuch a one is a compleat Gentleman, they will preſently, if Nature has be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon them any fluency of Language, make an Anatomy of him with their ſharp Tongues, in aim to Ruine, if they can, his Repute, as over-ſhaddowing theirs. They will tell you, if you call him a Schollar, he is a Pedant, if Eloquent, he ſpeaks much Non-ſenſe, if he be a Judge, he is Partial: if you ſay he is an Author, and diſtinguiſheth himſelf by his Learning, from the common ſort, he will then undoubtedly be a mark for envy to aim at, eſpecially if Native of the ſame Country, few being Prophets at home. They ſhall aſſure you his Works are not worth your while, though perhaps they never read what they condemn, and are not capable to write ſo well.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49595:11"/> We ſhould on this account, abſtain from cenſuring others, and not judge of Arts, till we be Artiſts. But ſuch is the malice of ſome, that what they cannot reach to, they blame through jealouſie in others: If you encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage ſuch by approving of, or adding to theſe Affronts, they put upon the Dead ſometimes, as well as the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, you ought to be accounted ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred as they are, and uncivil. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction ſo inconſiſtent, as we may gather out of the fore-going Lines, with the Rules of true Civility, is yet more ordinary amongſt Women, than among Men, becauſe they are generally an unthinking ſort of Creatures, and ſcarce reflecſive on what they ſay, being eaſily over-rul'd by their paſſions, and commonly not capable to revenge themſelves otherwiſe than with their Tongues.</p>
               <p>When they meet together in a familiar Converſe, after their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49595:11"/> Ceremonies, and mutual Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the price of every thing they wear: 'tis odds, but ſome of the company will take occaſion to ſay, <hi>Such a Lady, or ſuch a Gentlewoman, goes too fine, and far above her quality; ſhe is talk'd of on that account all the City over, as if ſhe had not all this for nothing, ſhe nevertheleſs will judge no body: but ſuch a thing is diſcours'd of in every Corner.</hi> The Ice being thus broken, another will utter her mind on the ſame matter more flatly, and call her baſe, infamous, and what not? as if ſhe were Innocency it ſelf, and not a Subject of diſcourſe to the World on the ſame account. For 'tis obſervable, the moſt debauch'd Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are proneſt to condemn others for Crimes they know themſelves guilty of.</p>
               <p>If they imagine they are injur'd by any perſon whatſomever, they will make (I may ſo ſay) an exact diſſection both of his Body and Soul,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49595:12"/> omitting nothing that rage can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent to black his Repute. Before they conceiv'd this Immortal hatred againſt him, they ſpoke to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage on all occaſions; but now, ſince 'tis his misfortune to diſpleaſe them, he hath loſt both his Wit and Judgment, he is ſilly, ſimple, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But this is only the defect of ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Women, ſeldom to, be met with in Ladies of a Noble Education, and Great Quality; whoſe Circles I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be the beſt Schools of Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, becauſe of an extraordinary complacency we are then reſolv'd to, in compliance to their Imperious Humours: There you ſhall hear them excuſe ingeniouſly the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections though never ſo real, of ſuch as are ill ſpoken of in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, becauſe they are fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to demean themſelves other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in ſuch Conjunctures, would prove a breach both of Charity and Civility.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:49595:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. V.</hi> Tis rudeneſs to be too talka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in Converſation.</head>
               <p>TO be too talkative in Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with our Friends, is a mark of a weak judgment, and prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to thoſe, who by an overthrow of that Order Nature has Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſpeak before they think, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, yea, moſt Women do, eſpecially thoſe of a Cholerick Complexion; ſuch are commonly moſt eloquent, or rather (if I may ſay ſo) moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, about trifles and ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whereon a judicious Man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the elevation of his Genius, finds nothing to ſay. What will they not ſay about a Hood, a Scarf, a <hi>Point de Venice?</hi> and how many words will they not ſpend to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs but little or no Senſe?</p>
               <p>You may obſerve them in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49595:13"/> little reflecſive on what is ſaid, but infinitely deſirous you put quickly an end to your Diſcourſe that they may commence their end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Tale, and often ſenſeleſs too. If they happen to be ſilenc'd by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whoſe Devil is more talkative than theirs, they become on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain ill humour'd, becauſe their Tongue is tyed up: but the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny once diſmiſt, if they can have Patience till then, they let it furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly looſe again againſt their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, or what-ever preſents it ſelf firſt to their ſight.</p>
               <p>Men are no leſs guilty of this Sin againſt the Laws of a civil Converſe, eſpecially thoſe of an advanc'd Age, who becauſe of their experience of things paſt, think it not lawful for greener years to ſpeak in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Their gray hairs I confeſs, exact of us a particular reſpect, and on this account 'tis civil to applaud ſometimes, through an Innocent
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49595:13"/> complacency to what they ſay, though we be of a contrary Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet on the other ſide, Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on requires they ſhould conſider they cannot be but importune to us, by their long and languiſhing Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, tending alwaies to the blame of preſent times, and praiſe of the paſt.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Laudator temporis acti—</l>
                  <l>Se puero, cenſor caſtigororque minorum.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Others will take not indeed the bit, but which is no leſs uncivil, the word out of your Mouth, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the end of your diſcourſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by an inſufferable rudeneſs, telling you to make haſte, to put an end: or more Ruſtick like yet, to be ſilent, and let them ſpeak; which is never lawful to do, unleſs thoſe we treat thus familiarly, be our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the loweſt rank.</p>
               <p>We muſt then in our Speech, as in our Actions, make choice of what is judg'd to be a middle between the two vicious extreams: for if Loqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49595:14"/> be forbidden us by the Rules of Civility, I am of Opinion, too much Taciturnity is no leſs contrary to it For if it be not the product of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Stupidity, 'tis alwaies an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent mark, we eſteem little thoſe we Converſe withal, which above all things we muſt ſhun, if we deſire to be accounted Civil. An obſtinate ſilence is affected prudently by ſome in Converſation; either to hide their little Talent of Elocution, or to gain more eſteem amongſt Men, who commonly admire moſt what they are leaſt acquainted with.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> That anger is againſt the Laws of a civil Converſe.</head>
               <p>AS moderation in our words and expreſſions, is the beſt diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can be imagin'd to a civil Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour in Converſation, ſo nothing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49595:14"/> more deſtructive to it than an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted paſſion, and a ſuddain an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, upon all Occurrencies: Some are as changeable as weather-Cocks in their humours, they know not what they would be at, and you can hardly ſay any thing that pleaſeth them. If you offer them your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and profeſs your zeal for their Concerns, they ſhall either return you no anſwer at all, or which is worſe, a diſobliging one, not reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what you have done for their Intereſt, but on ſome inconſiderable failures, you have perhaps admitted in the performance of that duty you are owing them.</p>
               <p>Such people are the peſts of all civil Converſe, and on this account, if in Civility we can, are to be ſhun'd. They are (I may ſo ſay) the incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ives of Quarrels, and reſtleſs Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers of all thoſe they Converſe with; the Standers by, look as amaz'd at one another, whileſt a Helliſh fury
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49595:15"/> vomits out a part of her ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour againſt either the Dead, or the abſent, or which is yet a greater rudeneſs, againſt ſome of thoſe which are preſent: ſuch are little behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Parents for their Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, they have never been curb'd in their Youth, and their being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies uſed to do their own will makes them now inſufferably wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
               <p>They often forget ſo far the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect they owe to Strangers though of an inferiour quality, that in their preſence upon all contingencies, they will rage and froth againſt their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, with moſt uncharitable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggerations of their leaſt, or fancied miſdemeanours: You ſhall hear them the whole time of a Dinner, whoſoever's at their Table, murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, repining, frowning at whom they know not, nor at what: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing relliſheth according to their taſte, none can ſerve them to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49595:15"/> the fall of a Spoon, of a Glaſs, or ſome like accident, puts them in, or rather quite out of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour again. What judgment can we frame of thoſe, in whom we obſerve ſuch continual Diſtempers? This diſcompoſure of their paſſions, hinders us to conceive either a great Opinion of their Vertue, or to love tenderly their Perſons.</p>
               <p>There is then a certain calm we muſt endevour to attain to in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, a certain peaceable tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per we muſt needs be poſſeſſ'd of, if we will neither be troubleſome to our ſelves, nor others. By this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration we ſhall gain Authority over thoſe we ſpeak to, and regain their eſteem, if perhaps by our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer indiſcretion we had loſt it; to demean our ſelves otherwiſe 'tis weakneſs, and holds too much of a Childiſh, or Womaniſh humour: though we cannot pull our paſſions out by the root, 'tis in our power to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49595:16"/> hold them down for a time at leaſt, whileſt we Converſe with our Friends, or Strangers: and who is not able to diſſemble thus far, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for all command, and not very apt neither to obey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VII.</hi> Obſtinacy in our proper ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is contrary to Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</head>
               <p>SOme are ſo poſſeſs'd with the Spirit of Contradiction, that they are ready to oppoſe whatever you ſhall advance, whether they think i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> true or falſe; They are falſly per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwaded they can take no better Me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thod, to convince you of the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs of their Wit, which ſometime I confeſs they do ſhow, but on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other ſide they loſe all the eſteem we had formerly conceived of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> judgment. This is the ordinary de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49595:16"/> of young and unexperienc'd Schollars, when they come firſt from the Univerſity, or as they ſay commonly, freſh off the Irons, they will undertake to prove every thing by a <hi>Sillogiſm in form,</hi> or an Argument in <hi>mode and figure.</hi> A little experience of the World, and ſome months Converſe with the judicious ſort, will ſoon rid them of this Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantick Air, ſo oppoſite to Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility, and common Senſe.</p>
               <p>I pretend not nevertheleſs to baniſh all diſputes, and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pancy of Opinions, from a civil Converſe: for that were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rational, nor poſſible, ſince <hi>Yes</hi> and <hi>No,</hi> are the very Soul and Life thereof. My deſign only here, is to Advertiſe you, we muſt ſubmit ſometimes our judgment to others, and ſhun upon all emergencies <hi>Obſtinacy,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49595:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49595:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49595:18"/> the product either of great <hi>Pride,</hi> or little <hi>Inſight:</hi> We may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our Reaſons with modeſty, which, if our Friends yield not to, we muſt Acquieſce, and let every Man abound in his own ſenſe.</p>
               <p>But to prevent prudently cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain neceſſary engagements, to ſtand ſtifly to our own ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, we muſt ſhun all debates in matters, not underſtood by thoſe we converſe with; for they being not perhaps humble enough to ſubmit to our judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will immediately oppoſe our ſentiments; and if ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to us in quality, pretend to the advantage by Authority, when reaſon ſerves not their turn. With theſe, I ſay, for reſts ſake, let us have no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, if we can avoid them, leaſt we betray either them, or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49595:18"/> our ſelves, to an uncivility.</p>
               <p>Conformably to this Rule, 'tis alwaies ſafer to ſubmit to the ſentiments of ſuch as we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on, tho' perhaps not ſo well grounded on reaſon, as our own; at leaſt if our familiarity with them permits us to oppoſe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times what they ſay, we muſt do it ſo, that without giving the leaſt advantage, we may ſtill ſeem to yield to them the debate: alledging for inſtance, his Lordſhip taketh the diſputed Point in ſuch or ſuch a ſenſe, in which we ſhall ſay, and ſhew 'tis a pure Truth: You, and his <hi>Grace,</hi> or his <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> being by this induſtry, of the ſame Opinion, you ſhall draw the whole company to a conſent without oppoſition.</p>
               <p>If we be at variance with our equals upon any diſputable
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49595:19"/> Point, we may diſpute it freely, ſhunning all rude and diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful expreſſions; that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear we pretend only to a clear diſcovery of the Truth, not to a Victory, or Triumph over our Friend, as our Enemy. If we debate, which we ſhould not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily do, with our inferiors, one thing particularly we muſt be aware of, not ſo much to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awe them by a contemptful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, as by a convincing reaſon; which, if we cannot perform, let us not diſcover by a ſuddain fit of anger, our ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cule Ambition, to appear in all we either ſay, or do, Infallible.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49595:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VIII.</hi> 'Tis inconſiſtent with Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to force Drink on a Stranger, or any other in the company.</head>
               <p>I Say, to force, for a kindly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation once, or twice, is ſo far from being a rudeneſs, that it is a neceſſary duty of Civility; I confeſs, this ſort of importunity is commonly the product of a noble, and generous Heart, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to welcome Strangers and Friends, at any rate: But if we reflect ſeriouſly on the undecen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the action in it ſelf, and the inconveniencies we expoſe our Friends to, by ſuch a cruel kindneſs, we ſhall inſtantly bluſh, and be aſham'd at our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49595:20"/> Civility, which, though your Friend cannot but take well, and as a kindneſs, becauſe of the Principle it comes from: yet, he cannot but be extreamly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended thereat, becauſe you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger by this violence, his Health, Life, and Repute: tho' this abomination is become now ſo general, that ſome glory in it, as if it were a honourable thing, and praiſe-worthy: which rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I obſerved no where ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, as in <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> and is I may ſay, without exaggerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the vileſt and moſt abſur'd can be imagin'd.</p>
               <p>I cannot compare this barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous cuſtom of forcing Drink upon Men, to a thing it reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles more, than Treaſon: for under a colourable pretence of Love, Kindneſs, and Eſteem, you betray your Friend. Firſt, to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49595:20"/> Sin, Secondly, to Contempt, Thirdly, to a Thouſand irregula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities; which a Man, if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves that Name, being now ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Beaſt, will be apt to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit in the heat of ſuch immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Riots. Yea, I ſay more, you are ſo far guilty of betraying your Friend, that you are (though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not deſignedly) the cauſe of his being either Robb'd, or Murder'd: at leaſt you expoſe him to ſuch miſchiefs, or which is all one, and no leſs to be feared, to a violent and ſuddain Death, by falling either in Fire or Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The <hi>French</hi> are to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended on this account, they Repute it, and with all reaſon, an unparallelable rudeneſs, to force a cup upon any Man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond that meaſure he judgeth ſufficient for his Health, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Neceſſity: amongſt them
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49595:21"/> you have your freedom, all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint in a civil Converſe being judged intollerable, every Man behaves himſelf in this caſe as he thinks fitteſt, he is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected on, whether he taketh leſs or more: and being left to his own diſcretion, if he exceed, he can blame none, but himſelf.</p>
               <p>I wiſh the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who are ſo far above the <hi>French,</hi> in other things, would but equal them in this one, I mean in their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and behaviour, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Strangers and Friends: who, ſometimes through a duty of good Neighbourhood, and Civility, muſt repair to their Houſes. The ſame rudeneſs is but too ordinary in <hi>Scotland,</hi> amongſt the Gentry, though otherwiſe exactly civil, and well bred. If you pay there a viſit to a Gentleman, or Nobleman,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49595:21"/> in his own Houſe, he will have in readineſs, or at a call, if he thinks not himſelf able to do your turn, two or three ſtout Drinkers, pitch'd upon deſigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to hold to your head: This Commiſſion they will perform with all diligence by a general Conſpiracy, to your utter ruine, you are without delay aſſaulted on all ſides. Firſt, with the ſtrongeſt Ale, then with Brandy, at laſt with Wine, till at length overcome, you are forc'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, and leave them victorious on the wet Fields, where they will triumph a while, till one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another, they be either led or carried off, to vent the fumes of theſe heady Liquors.</p>
               <p>Now, if there be any thing in this procedure looking like humanity, we muſt extinguiſh in us, the unbred light of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49595:22"/> and confeſs againſt all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe, the greateſt Civility is only to be met with in the practice of the moſt brutiſh and extravagant Debauchery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IX.</hi> To ſpeak too high is againſt the Maxims of a civil Converſe.</head>
               <p>THe reaſon of this is obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, becauſe by crying aloud, or ſpeaking with an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated Tone, we diſcover our ambition to be conſider'd, and harken'd to, according to that of the Poet, <hi>Vult digito monſtrari &amp; dicier hic eſt.</hi> Now Pride, as I made appear, elſewhere is the ſource of all our miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and moſt of all deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49595:22"/> to Civility; ſuch a rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as this we are now ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, is more inſufferable in Churches, and thoſe places, where we ſhould ſpeak either little or none at all: as likewiſe in preſence of Princes, and our other Superiours, we ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to reverence by a reſpectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſilence, than diſquiet by our boiſterous clamours.</p>
               <p>The deformity of this ſort of immodeſty, is repreſented to Life, by the ruder ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, gathered together in an Ale-houſe, or any other Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly: there you ſhall hear them ſpeaking all together, and with ſuch a confuſion, that you ſhall hear none of them diſtinctly. They call aloud one another by their Names or nick-Names, in a ruſtick and homely manner, and make commonly ſuch a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49595:23"/> noiſe, that thoſe who paſs by, ſtand to liſten if they quarrel not: as ſuch people were ever, and are ſtill Reputed moſt rude, we muſt with a watchful circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection over our own behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, ſhun this barbarous way of Converſing; to which we may reduce all noiſe whatſomever in preſence of our Friends, whether it be with our hands, feet, or otherwiſe: As alſo, a certain im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſt ſort of laughter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we either diſcover our own inconſiderateneſs, or that we are regardleſs of the company. The Precept of the ancient <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher</hi> muſt be followed in this caſe, <hi>Riſus nec ſit multus, nec ob multa nec effuſus.</hi> To laugh too much is the Character of a childiſh and fooliſh Humour, to laugh on every ſlight Occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, betrayeth us to be light and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49595:23"/> ſilly: but to laugh as Women do ſometimes, with our hands on both ſides, and with a laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious agitation of our whole Body, is the height of rudeneſs and immodeſty; remember then, and practiſe that Golden Sentence, <hi>Riſus non ſit multus, nec ob multa nec eſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. X.</hi> That frequent Oaths are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with Civility.</head>
               <p>I Can conceive nothing more rude, than this barbarous or rather Heatheniſh cuſtom ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral in this Age, of taking the Name of God in vain, or calling him as a Witneſs to every inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant and impertinent propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, we raſhly advance. I have obſerved three great abuſes
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49595:24"/> in this matter, point blanck con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary not only to Godlineſs, but alſo to good manners: ſome with great precipitancy, atteſt every Truth they ſay, by ſolemn Oaths, as if they could not otherwiſe gain truſt. Others again, and theſe are worſe than the firſt, ſwear with all imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable confidence, what to their certain Science and Conſcience is moſt falſe, which is a Crime amounting to ſuch a high mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of malice, that in Charity, I ſhall ſuppoſe no rational Man to be ever guilty of it. There is a third ſort that fills, or rather fouls the Ears of thoſe that hear them, with a perpetual curſed Nonſenſe of <hi>God Damning, Sink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Confounding,</hi> or ſuch like Unchriſtian and Nonſenſical ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions.</p>
               <p>That ſuch Immortal practices
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49595:24"/> are the meer products of rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or uncivility; 'tis ſo evident, that I need not be at the pains to prove it, ſince every one is taught this Truth by the light of Nature, as uncapable to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us, as the Author of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture himſelf: for amongſt whom, I pray ye, are Oaths moſt uſual? amongſt thoſe only we look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the very ſcum of the World? and if I may ſo ſay, the very excrementitious part of Mankind? If then others conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, either for their Birth, Riches, or Learning, be ſubject ſometimes to this diſorder, as I confeſs, but too many of them are; they are deſervedly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued by the underſtanding ſort, and all ſuch as are natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly averſe from rudeneſs.</p>
               <p>After a ſerious enquiry into the cauſes of this diſorder, I can
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49595:25"/> imagine, none that looks like a rational inducement to ſuch an abominable cuſtom. For, 1. I am ſure there is leſs pleaſure in it than in any other Sin what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. 2. No Man in his Wits, can pretend to be more truſted, the more he ſwears, ſince 'tis an undoubted of Truth, that the greateſt Swearers are commonly the greateſt Liars. 3. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of Wit, can methinks allure no Man, to put on ſuch an ill and vile habit: is not Stupidity it ſelf as capable thereof, as the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Wit of the World? 4. A ſhew perhaps of courage and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is the end ſome propoſe to themſelves by theſe Imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and threatning Oaths: But how far they fall ſhort of their aim, judge by this, that Men commonly make ſmall account of theſe great Boaſters, and think
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49595:25"/> them deſtitute of true courage, yea, and great Cowards.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XI.</hi> When Railery is conſiſtent, and when inconſiſtent with Civility.</head>
               <p>'TIs alwaies the greateſt rudeneſs imaginable, to play upon ſacred things, as Church Ceremonies, our dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Myſteries, and Divine Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: this is the true Character of a Man, that neither loves God, nor Godlineſs, neither is Railery decent or lawful, if it reflect upon the natural defects of our Neighbours, or to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in preſence of Princes, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by their great intimacy with us, they make us an
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49595:26"/> overture of a not ordinary fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity.</p>
               <p>'Tis as yet more inſufferable, when we converſe with Ladies, eſpecially in matters relating to that Vertue they ſhould look upon as the chief, if not the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ornament of their Sex: yet, this is a common rudeneſs, and covers ſometimes ſmiſter deſigns, under the Names of Complacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Gallantry: in which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar way of Converſing, ſome go ſuch a length, as to paſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all the limits of modeſty, by their rough and flat expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of theſe undecencies, you hear but too often, and modeſty cauſeth me to conceal.</p>
               <p>If Railery then muſt be made uſe of, 'tis with thoſe that are either our equals, or have made us ſuch by their privacy, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate friendſhip; yet, leaſt we
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49595:26"/> fail, we are to reflect ſeriouſly upon three things: we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the firſt, in the ſecond, the perſons we ſpeak with, and the third, regards the fitteſt ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for this innocent Mirth. We muſt firſt conſider if Nature has allowed us theſe qualities, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, we cannot pretend to a good ſucceſs in this way of Converſing; which may, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, be reduc'd to theſe three; A faculty eaſily reflexive upon every contingency, a quick ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, and a ſharpneſs of wit not ordinary. If Nature has uſed us ſo kindly, as to have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to us theſe her favours in any conſiderable meaſure, we would diſoblige her to hide our Talent, or deprive our Friends of that innocent joy, we are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to procure 'em: but if we find no ſuch diſpoſitions in us,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49595:27"/> or no ray of that extemporary ſubtilty, neceſſary for a ſuddain attack, ſurprize, repartee; let us abſtain from Railery, leaſt to our ſhame and confuſion, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn by reflex upon our ſelves. The ſecond thing we are to take notice of, is, the perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons we are in converſe with: if we judge them not ſharp enough to conceive at the firſt, <hi>a point d'leſprit,</hi> a ſenſeful and witty word, we muſt deal plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſeriouſly with ſuch men, waving all in <hi>promptu's</hi> and <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties,</hi> they could not underſtand without a commentary. The third thing to be conſider'd is, the ſeaſon fitteſt for Railery, we muſt make choice of thoſe hours our Friends are freeſt from cares, and beſt diſpos'd to mirth: for otherwiſe you would be thought extreamly rude, to ſay no more,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49595:27"/> if in lieu of a Complement of condoleance to your Friend, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Death of his Wife, or his Child, you would undertake to diſſipate his juſt melancholy by an unſeaſonable Railery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XII.</hi> That exceſſive Flattery is a great rudeneſs.</head>
               <p>THere are two dangerous extreams, to either of which we incline through vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, rather than judgment; The firſt is Flattery, the other is Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm, or a cenſorious humour, condemning indifferently every thing, that we may appear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by undervaluing that which is above the reach of our limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Capacity. Theſe two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49595:28"/> we muſt by all means a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void, and ſearch a middle, which I take to be a <hi>rational complacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> I ſay deſignedly <hi>rational,</hi> for if it want this Character, it will cauſe us to put on a reſolution to be complaiſant at any rate in all Occurrencies, with all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to what is bad, as well as to what is good, which could amount to nothing elſe but a vile, baſe, and fervile Flattery: whereby we loſe our Credit, and are laught at by the judicious ſort, and ſometimes undervalued by thoſe we intend moſt to gain, by theſe flat, and officious Lies.</p>
               <p>Yet, becauſe Men are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted with what ever contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes towards the encreaſe of their Honour, we muſt withal reſpect pay to them upon fit occaſions the Homage of praiſe, but only upon the account of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49595:28"/> their real merits, as their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and acquired Talents, their great actions in Peace and War, at home and abroad, their uſeful Writings and Enterpriſes, for the common good, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such deſerved praiſes are not to be blam'd, as making up a part of the civil Man, but theſe only we are preſs'd to by an unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable deſire, to pleaſe at any rate thoſe we are converſant with, of which end nevertheleſs, we fall commonly ſhort; for, though our Friends ſeem to countenance our diſcourſe with a ſmile or two, perhaps they rank us in their Hearts amongſt the ſimple, airy, and light bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt ſort of Men.</p>
               <p>Women above all others, are ſubject to be impos'd upon by Flattery, whether it be that they have a great conceit of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49595:29"/> Endowments in what meaſure ſoever they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them from God, or whether it comes from an innocent plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure they take, to hear their young airy Gallants diſplay a World of Nonſenſe in polite terms, or whether ſome of them are ſo ſimple, as to truſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggerations of a paſſionate Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: who, becauſe of this perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that he either is believ'd or pleaſeth, thinks he has ſaid little to the commendation of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris, unleſs he put the <hi>Lillies, Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> out of countenance in her preſence. Such Affections, and ſpecious Nonſenſe, ought never to be made uſe of by ſuch as pretend to be a part of the civil World, nor liſten'd to by modeſt, and virtuous Ladies. Yet, becauſe they delight exceedingly in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49595:29"/> hearing their own praiſes, we may withal moderation, and proportionably to their merits, rather than quality, perform without great expence, this part of our duty towards that weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Sex: I have as yet one thing to ſay worth your reflection, That Flattery, provided it be not exceſſive, is more ſufferable, and ſometimes to be allowed of in Servants towards their Maſters, and in Children towards their Parents: becauſe the Kindneſs of a Maſter, is ordinarily gain'd, and the tender Affection of a a Father or Mother, increaſed by theſe Teſtimonies of Love from their Servants and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p>Before I conclude this <hi>Section,</hi> I ſhall ſay one word of <hi>Criticiſm</hi> the other extream. Thoſe that are of a too Critical humour,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49595:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:49595:30"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49595:31"/> are not reckon'd up with the Civil ſort, becauſe they uſurp an inſufferable Empire, and an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Authority, over the whole World, their ſuperiors as well as their equals; they approve of nothing, and of none but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they are alwaies ready to make comments, and malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant reflections on what ever is ſaid, and will have nothing to paſs as conformable to common Senſe and Reaſon, what they judge not ſo. If they have any ſuperficial tincture of Littera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I pity the beſt of Authors, they ſhall cenſure and ſentence them, though perhaps they are no more acquainted with them, than with thoſe they had never ſeen; If any thing that gets a Name appear in Print, they ſhall ſtrike at it through envy in all occaſions, and pretend, becauſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49595:31"/> they can ſay what an Old Wife may ſay too, <hi>'tis no great matter,</hi> to have as great capacity, and inſight in the ſubject, as the Author himſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XIII.</hi> How we may ſhun the two forementioned extreams, <hi>Flattery</hi> and <hi>Criticiſm.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FLattery</hi> we ſhall eaſily ſhun, by obſerving the following Precepts. 1. To ſay nothing to any Mans advantage but what is true. 2. To abſtain from all affected exaggerations. 3. To pay the Homage of our praiſes in convenient time and place. Some have ſo weak a diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faculty, that they never take notice by what byaſs Mens
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49595:32"/> Hearts are ſooner conquer'd: they commonly fancy the Art of pleaſing conſiſts in flat and officious lies, not reflecting that judicious Men are ſometimes no leſs offended by falſe and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd praiſes, than by contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and calumniatory Imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and certainly with all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: For, ſince none but Fools delight in flat untruths ſpoken to their advantage, how can they take it patiently to be thought of this number, though called infinite in Scripture? Such muſt be your Opinion of a Man you extoll highly to his face for great things he never dream'd on: by this Childiſh procedure, you either betray your own folly, or his, if you believe him in his Wits: for than you may expect to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd rather than rewarded, <hi>his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49595:32"/> folly,</hi> by cauſing the By-ſtanders to ſuſpect he takes pleaſure in ſuch Notorious Lies: which would be a mortal blow to his Repute.</p>
               <p>You muſt avoid with no leſs care, theſe two ordinary and childiſh exaggerations of the Truth, which in reality amount to nothing elſe but to as many magnificent Untruths: cannot ye praiſe for inſtance, a Lady, upon the account of her Beauty, unleſs ye call her a <hi>Deity;</hi> A <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> unleſs ye ſay he is an <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> a <hi>Poet,</hi> an <hi>Orator,</hi> unleſs they be <hi>Virgils, Ovids, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero's,</hi> and beyond them too: may we not ſpeak before a great Captain, and to his advantage; though we tell him not pomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly. <hi>The paſt Ages furniſh us with no example of Warlike Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits conſiderable in compare to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49595:33"/> his, that we are fully perſwaded he ſhall be a ſcope to Envy in all future times.</hi> This you ſee is too much, and therefore nothing at all: let your <hi>Elogium</hi>'s in your Converſe, be alwaies within the circumference of common Senſe and Reaſon, that thoſe ye praiſe may be perſwaded you think what you ſay. Some again fall into another inconveniency, no leſs to be ſhun'd, than the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going; They affect to run out in praiſe of their Friends upon all occaſions, without regard to ſeveral circumſtances, wherein ſilence would be thought more ſeaſonable. This I confeſs, may be Laudable and Arbitrary in their abſence, but when they are preſent, you muſt obſerve two things; 1. Remember not to touch alwaies upon the ſame ſtring, I mean not to weary
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49595:33"/> your Friend with an idle Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of his merits, great acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, capacity, talents, for that would create a diſguſt of your Converſe, becauſe of ſuch a viſible affectation. 2. To be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of your Complements be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Rivals, or declared Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, becauſe the former would conceive againſt you, a not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary hatred, as favouring thoſe they love not, and the latter would defame you every where, as an intereſs'd Flatterer.</p>
               <p>As to <hi>Criticiſm,</hi> you need do no other thing to avoid it, but only put on a firm Reſolution to reſiſt in all occaſions your cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring <hi>Genius;</hi> or if you be a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanthrop</hi> in ſuch a meaſure, that you can praiſe nothing that is praiſe worthy, you may at leaſt Command your unruly Tongue to be ſilent, unleſs your ſilence,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49595:34"/> as it happens frequently, prove an evident mark of your diſdain; for in this juncture you are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Law of Civility to commend, what in reaſon you cannot blame.</p>
               <p>Remember, your cenſorious humour will cauſe every one to ſhun your company, leaſt as ye talk at random of others, you Treat them after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in their abſence: If you had but two Ounces of common Senſe, you would eaſily be wrought into ſome feeling of your folly in this Point; for as you cenſure others, ſo likewiſe ſhall you be cenſur'd by turn, as you diſprove what others do or ſay, they, through a juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, ſhall obſerve with a pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Eye, and diſcover the leaſt of your failures. As you miſ-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret their beſt intentions,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49595:34"/> your ſiniſter deſigns ſhall at length be laid open, or if good, miſconſtrued. Forget not then that moſt juſt command, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Principle: <hi>Quod tibi non vis fieri, alteri ne feceris,</hi> do as you would be done to.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XIV.</hi> That we ought to conform our Diſcourſe to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of thoſe we Converſe.</head>
               <p>IF we deſire to be agreeable to thoſe we Converſe, we muſt ſtudy with all diligence their humours, ſound their inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and not regard what we but what they take moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in; for otherwiſe we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive often our ſelves, conceiving
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49595:35"/> ſometimes we are acceptable to all, while we are troubleſome, and pleaſe none but our ſelves: and this alwaies happens, when like talkative Women, we lull people aſleep with our long and tedious Diſcourſes, ſcarce fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſenſibly our breath, ſo faſt we run, and never giving time to any of the company to edg in a word. When this happens in <hi>France,</hi> they will offer you Money in a jeſt, to let them have a while to ſpeak at their turn.</p>
               <p>We are often of Opinion af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a long Narrative, which a ſolid judgment had concluded in three or four words, that all the By-ſtanders admire us, and take us to be the fitteſt humours for Converſe they could meet with; but how far we are impoſed upon by our own credulous ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49595:35"/> we may judge by our proper experience, if ever we have ſuffered, as no doubt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we have a ſort of long Martyrdom, by the Tiranny of of theſe Domeſtick Enemies, who are wont to put an end to our Patience with their endleſs and fabulous Tales. Purpos'd we not then to be upon our guards another time, leaſt we ſhould be redacted into the ſame ſtraits again; and if we are put to the ſame torture in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture, we cannot Civilly fhun. By a profitable foreſight, we give a Secret Commiſſion to ſome of our Friends or Servants, to come to our relief, with ſome colourable pretence of a Friend, or an urgent Affair calling us other where.</p>
               <p>Let us here reflect that what we ſuffer in this caſe, we cauſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49595:36"/> others to ſuffer, and more too by that perpetual movement of our unruly Tongue: conſider alwaies the condition of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons you converſe withal, and fit dextrouſly your Diſcourſe to their capacity and ſtrongeſt inclinations: as for inſtance, If you are to entertain a General of an Army, <hi>Battels, Sieges, Stratagems, Cannoning, Mining, Retrenching, Fortifying,</hi> &amp;c. will open unto you a vaſt Field to run out upon, and a ſubject charmingly pleaſant to him you ſpeak to, whom you ſhall leave ſatisfied, and deſirous to meet with you again; but remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not to play the Maſter in an Art, wherein (as I ſuppoſe) he is experienc'd, and which you have but a meer ſpeculative knowledge of, you muſt then Diſcourſe of all this as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49595:36"/> to learn, not to teach.</p>
               <p>If you converſe with a Man of a Noble and Ancient Family, mind him of his Anceſtors, of their great Alliances, Glory, and Actions, ſhow your ſelf well vers'd in his Lineage, and well read in the Hiſtory of his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for this hath ſomewhat of bewitching, and pleaſeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely.</p>
               <p>I had great intimacy with a <hi>French</hi> Gentleman, who had this Talent, and no other in a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Degree: when he came to ſettle any time in a City, his ſtudy was to ſearch into the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Pedegrees of every conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Family, and in Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, made uſe of this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with ſuch dexterity, as to ſhew to all their concernments ſtill by the faireſt ſide, giving an accurate account of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49595:37"/> Predeceſſors, of their decay, or encreaſe; which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to be exceedingly loved by all, and look'd upon as the only capable Judge of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates about precedencies, and ſuch like <hi>Punctilo's</hi> of Honour.</p>
               <p>We muſt not imagine all is well, when we have contented our ſelves; but though we be unſatisfied, when we have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the ſatisfaction of others, by diſcourſing of things they can eaſily, and delight moſt to diſcourſe of: for we would be Reputed rude and impertinent, if we entertain'd for inſtance, a Lady, with <hi>Phyloſophical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems, Preciſions</hi> of our Reaſon, and <hi>Metaphyſical Beings;</hi> the very Names of ſuch things, and all barbarous School Terms, are to be ſhun'd by the polite ſort, who would take pleaſure to hear
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49595:37"/> a Man exorciſing in a manner, thoſe he ſpeaks to, with theſe harſh words: <hi>Categonimatice, Sincategonematice, ut quo, ut quod, materialiter, formaliter,</hi> and other ſuch like pedantick expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
               <p>Out of all this we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe five things, enſuing to be indiſpenſibly neceſſary in a perfect Artiſt of the Civil Mode. 1. A knowledge of no leſs extent than that of an <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</hi> 2. A quick and clear ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginative faculty to conceive things in an inſtant, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out confuſion. 3. A ſolid judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to diſcern the truth from the meer appearance thereof. 4. A mortified will, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to learn rather than to teach, to ſpeak conformably to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh of others more than our own: which is not ſo to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49595:38"/> but if we are required to inſtruct, we muſt do it <hi>Cum ſpecimine ingenii &amp; modeſtiae</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, and modeſtly, yet with a ſhow of our Capacity and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight in the matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XV.</hi> That 'tis a Duty of Civility to converſe ſometimes with our Friends by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</head>
               <p>THat 'tis a part of our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Write ſometimes to our Friends, every one may clearly underſtand by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant practice of all ſuch as are accounted in every Nation the Models of Civility; we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them by this Officiouſneſs of our ſincere Love, which could
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49595:38"/> ſeem intereſs'd or ceremonial when they were preſent. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſince Friends cannot be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies together, their abſence is ſupplied by Letters, without which, the ſtrongeſt Friendſhip will at length decay; for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more true than what is now become Proverbial, <hi>Out of ſight, out of mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in what manner we muſt acquit ourſelves of this ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary a Duty towards our Friends, 'tis not eaſie to declare: yet ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally we may ſay, whether our Letters be meerly Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, or of Affairs, they muſt alwaies bear a certain proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Firſt, To the matter we Writ of: Secondly, To the perſons we Writ to: and Thirdly, To our own condition. This Rule com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends all other particulars, which cannot be uſefully ſet
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49595:39"/> down, but are to be left to each Mans particular judgment; I ſay, nevertheleſs we muſt ſhun the defects above mentioned, in our ordinary converſe with our Friends preſent, ſince we are apt to fall into ſeveral of the ſame in our Letters. <hi>Firſt,</hi> We ought to avoid ſcrupulouſly whatever tends to our own Praiſe direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or indirectly, as certain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions whereby we may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear too deſirous of eſteem, which defect is obſervable in <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero</hi> and moſt of the <hi>Antients,</hi> but in this they are not to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let us take care our Letters contain nothing <hi>Satyrical,</hi> or tending to the ſtain of our Neighbours good Name. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As in our Diſcourſes, ſo in our Letters, Prolixity is never allowed of, idle Digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſuperfluous Repetitions,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49595:39"/> and ſuch like Exorbitancies, ought to be retrench'd, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if we write to thoſe that have but few ſpare moments from their own Affairs or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Employments. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Tho' a Letter bluſh not, we muſt be aſham'd to diſcover therein our weakneſs, by wrathful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, bitter Invectives, Oaths and Curſes. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> A too exceſſive Flattery is far from the Character of an exact and judicious Letter, we may nevertheleſs be more prodigal of our praiſes when we write, than when we ſpeak in preſence. <hi>Sixthly,</hi> As to the ſtile and manner of writing 'tis alwaies irregular, unleſs it be Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable; 1. To the ſubject we write of; 2. To our preſent condition; 3. To the quality of thoſe we write to; If the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49595:40"/> require a ſerious deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all intermixture of Jeſt will be unſeaſonable: If the perſon we write to is much above our quality, we muſt pay to him exactly, yet without Affectation, the Homage of a due Reſpect. If our preſent and preſſant exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies oblige us to implore the help of ſuch as may ſupply our wants, let our Letter contain true and forcing motives; but to ſay all in one word, for parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Precepts are numberleſs, we muſt reflect upon all the Circumſtances that engage us to this Duty, and from them take our meaſures Conformably to the Rules of Civility, and our own particular Deſigns.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:49595:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XVI.</hi> That all Jeſt or Earneſt tending to Impiety, is an extream rudeneſs.</head>
               <p>'TIs not now as of Old, when the Wicked ſaid only in his Heart, <hi>There is no God;</hi> ſome, yea and too many, dare defend it openly in publick Aſſemblies, pretending on this account to be look'd upon as Wits capable to Diſpute Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; Of all thoſe you converſe with, you ſhall meet with none more void, both of Chriſtian and Civil Nurture, than this ſort of Men.</p>
               <p>Such Extravagants, for I know not what other Name to give them, betray themſelves to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49595:41"/> the hatred and contempt of the Godly and underſtanding ſort, they are look'd upon, and with all reaſon, as deſtitute of all true Wit and Vertue, becauſe they neither acknowledge a Reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Vertues, nor a Puniſher of Crimes; they are not come this length in an Inſtant, <hi>Nemo deripente fit peſſimus,</hi> but by Degrees, adding Sin to Sin. And laſtly, <hi>Atheiſm</hi> to the heap, the greateſt of all Sins, as being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Divine Faith, the only Ground-Stone of our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Building; whenſoever any Man forgets himſelf ſo far as to ſay any thing, whether it be in Jeſt or Earneſt, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this Fundamental Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of our Faith, <hi>There is a God,</hi> all complacency laid aſide, you ought to reprove him gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly as rude and impious, I ſay
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49595:41"/> as rude or uncivil in a Soveraign Degree; for reflecting on it, you ſhall obſerve, that all ſuch as either in Jeſt or Earneſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a God, demean themſelves in a manner, point blanck con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Maxims above mentioned, of a Civil converſe. For 1. Their Diſcourſe is nothing elſe but Self-praiſe; 2. They ſpeak ill of all, God himſelf not excepted; 3. They are talkative beyond meaſure, tho' they ſay juſt nothing; 4. They are prone to anger, and at the firſt attack fall into a fury; 5. Their ordinary converſe is like the roaring of a raging Sea, unquiet and tumultuous; 6. 'Tis a loſs of time to oppoſe their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable ſentiments, they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yield to common Senſe nor Reaſon, how evident ſoever; 7. They'l force you if they can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49595:42"/> their ſentiments, and the ſame Debaucheries; 8. They are not content with ordinary Oaths, they invent new ones, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver as yet heard of, nor thought on perhaps by the Devil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; 9. Becauſe they cannot wholly extinguiſh the inbred knowledge of a Deity, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to be rid of all fear of his Juſtice in the other, World by ranking themſelves in the order of Beaſts, as to the State of their Souls after Death; they will tell you flatly, they believe no ſuch thing as an Immortal Soul, whereby they diſcover their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires rather than their ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: becauſe if nothing of 'em had a Being capable of feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after Death, they would thereby ſhun the puniſhment they deſerve for their Sins.</p>
               <p>If then there can be any
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49595:42"/> rudeneſs parallelable to that of theſe abominable <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all Men of a ſound Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if you will not endanger, yea, undoubtedly loſe your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, and which is much more to be valued, your Soul; you muſt fly ſwiftly from ſuch Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, <hi>tanquam a facie celubri,</hi> as if they were <hi>Venemous Serpents</hi> and <hi>Baſilicks,</hi> killing with their very ſight.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. XVII.</hi> That 'tis an extream rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſpeak to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage of any Nation, in preſence of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives.</head>
               <p>I Can imagine no rudeneſs more inſufferable, than to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49595:43"/> fall foul upon any Nation, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in Jeſt or Earneſt, in preſence of the very Natives, becauſe, beſides that every Man is extreamly concern'd in the Honour of his own Country, <hi>neſcio qua natale ſolem dulcedine cunctos allicit,</hi> Men are apt to look upon ſuch reproaches as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning by reflex upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; we are then indiſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly obliged by all the Laws of Civility, to give Forraigners all imaginable encouragements to love us, and truſt to us, not only by ſaying nothing derogatory to the Honour of their Nation, which we muſt alwaies be aware of, but affecting rather to praiſe it upon the account of theſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that every Country pretends to, above another. This is the Practice of all noble Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and true Gentlemen, they
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49595:43"/> do in this caſe as they would be done to, and love Wit and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue where-ever they ſee it; who behave themſelves other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, are either ill bred at home, or have never been abroad.</p>
               <p>'Tis an Infallible mark of a baſe and barbarous Education, to undervalue a Man only upon the account he is a Stranger, ſince this Character, if we have not put off all ſentiments of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, ſhould rather induce us to love him, and prompt us to ſerve him upon all occaſions; let us reflect how we would be dealt with, if we were in For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Nations, and we ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly know what we have to do in this caſe; would we not be touch'd to the very quick, if any Man were ſo incivil, as to reproach to us the defects true or falſe, of our Native Soil?
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49595:44"/>
'tis odd, but we would retaliate in the Inſtant. You mind than to quarrel, and not to behave your ſelf civilly, when ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to Strangers the defaults of their Country they are not guilty of: but becauſe 'tis or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to ſpeak to the diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of our Neighbours, not that we believe what we ſay, but through a particular preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice one Nation has alwaies had againſt another, if we find any ſuch Diſpoſition, or Averſion in us, we muſt do what lies in our power to ſtifle it before Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, leaſt we give them juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to complain of our incivili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and aſcribe to the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion our particular imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>To this we may add, 'tis a great rudeneſs, after we have Travell'd through Forreign
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49595:44"/> Kingdoms, to make up our <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs</hi> only with fancied <hi>Indeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rums,</hi> ridiculing for diverſion of the company, all their particular Cuſtoms; By ſuch <hi>Satyrical</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections we may give ſome proof of our Wit, but at the ſame time we diſcover our little Judgement, and much of a Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Paſſion.</p>
               <p>Some Nations I confeſs are more compleat than others; and more conſiderable for their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, Riches, Warlike Exploits, Sharpneſs, Policy, and Polity, yet if we weigh all things on each ſide impartialy, we ſhall not have ſo great reaſon as we fancy, to prefer our ſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Neighbours, for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly if we ſurpaſs them in one thing, we do not in all, but are often ſurpaſs'd by them in others again, no leſs, if not more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49595:45"/> This Reflection ſhould force us to uſe all kindly, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Strangers, on whoſe love and eſteem our Repute, and that of our Nation depends.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="article">
            <head>ARTICLE. III.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTION. I.</hi> Of the familiar Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</head>
               <p>IT ſeems there is no Art to be made uſe of in a familiar Converſation, that here we are to obſerve no Precepts, but only to behave our ſelves with all freedom, and do whatever Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture inclineth us moſt too; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs if we call to mind what I have ſaid elſewhere, that we muſt ſtill endeavour to gain
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49595:45"/> the love and eſteem of thoſe we converſe with, we ſhall eaſily be perſwaded that in this homely way of converſing, we muſt be no leſs cautious, yea, more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act than in any other, to obſerve ſuch Precepts as have been judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neceſſary in all Ages to the entertaining of a real Friendſhip. The firſt is, That whatſoever love we have for our Friends, or they for us, we never truſt to it ſo far as to betray our ſelves to their Contempt, by too great familiarity; If they be our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Princes, what ever Friendſhip they make ſhew of to us, let us alwaies behave our ſelves, as if we could not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of their Affection upon the account of our unworthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; yet if they will have us to leave the Ceremonial Method of a reſpectuous Friendſhip, we
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49595:46"/> may then ſpeak with more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom our ſentiments, obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt to give them alwaies the advantage, whether it be on their ſide or not. 2. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur with them in nothing, as if we pretended to be their Rivals: This Ambition, or rather Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, has been the Ruine of many Courtiers in all Ages, who preſuming too much upon their Princes Friendſhip, would ſhare with him in every thing, yea, in his very Amours.</p>
               <p>The Second Rule we are to obſerve in a familiar Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whether it be with our Equals or Superiours, is, never to ſpeak of ſuch things as we ought to be aſham'd of before Men, and repent for in the ſight of God: Such are your By-paſt Debaucheries, Pleaſures, and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots. This is nevertheleſs a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49595:46"/> and too ordinary defect, amongſt Perſons of Quality, if they be in any degree familiar; you ſhall hear them boaſting of things I abhor to think on, and dare not name, as if they pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Repute of honeſty, by ſuch infamous and effeminate Exploits. They are falſly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded you are in a high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of their Valour, when they have told you how many Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries they have got, not in the Fields of <hi>Mars,</hi> but in the Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of their only God <hi>Bacchus;</hi> one would think they pretend to as much Honour for drinking a Man out of his Wits, as if they had forc'd an Enemy out of his Hold.</p>
               <p>The Third Rule we muſt ſquare our familiar converſe by is, not to make our intimacy with either Man or Woman what-ſome-ever,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49595:47"/> an occaſion of calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or detraction, which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs is but too uſual when we are come from an ordinary friendſhip, to a certain degree of familiarity; we open then our Hearts and keep nothing cloſe, yea, not the very Secrets of others truſted to us, which ſometimes we diſcover to all we can meet with under a tye of a Secret; For this reaſon we muſt diſcover nothing to the Wife, what we would have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to her Husband, nor to to the Husband, what we would not have his Wife acquainted with, becauſe (as we may ſay) they are two Bodies in one Fleſh, ſo they are two Souls in one Spirit, by a certain transfuſion of their Hearts.</p>
               <p>It happens then but too often, that an exceſſive and irregular
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49595:47"/> familiarity induceth us to the diſcovery of things that ſhould be kept moſt Secret; from whence it is that we ſpare none in our familiar converſe, yea, not thoſe whom diſſemblingly we admire whilſt we are in their preſence.</p>
               <p>The Fourth Rule we ought to obſerve exactly, is, to keep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably the Secret our Friend hath truſted us with, unleſs it be inconſiſtent with the ſafety of either our Prince, or Country we live in, for in this caſe no tye of friendſhip can oblige us to their prejudice; but in all other Conjunctures we are Traytors, if we betray our Friends, or their Secrets; And this is not only to be underſtood of theſe things they deſire us earneſtly to keep to our ſelves, but of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others they commend not
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49595:48"/> to our Secrecy, which common Senſe teacheth us never to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover. If you converſe famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly with a Woman, keep cloſe from her what you would not have known to the whole World: for though ſome of them may, and do keep a Secret, yet few of them are capable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal their thoughts a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able time and in all occaſions, becauſe they ſpeak commonly, eſpecially the more fiery ſort, before they think, or at leaſt in the very inſtant; ſo they either utter their mind without <hi>reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or reflect only on what they ſay in the very moment of their utterance, when but too late they would fain hold in what is now by half a word ſufficiently underſtood.</p>
               <p>The Fifth Rule is, not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume ſo much on our Friends
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49595:48"/> good Nature, as to think we cannot anger him whatever we do, and ſo play upon his Natural defects, or diſprove whatever he ſaies or does. If we will ſuffer nothing in others our importunity will be trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to them, and may perhaps occaſion a wide breach of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; let us not then imagine that familiarity in what degree ſoever it be, gives us a full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to uſe and abuſe our Friend at pleaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Of the Learned Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</head>
               <p>THe Learned Converſe is either deſign'd, as when Scholars meet together to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49595:49"/> ſome Scholaſtick Point, or 'tis accidental when occaſionally we joyn in company with ſuch as are well grounded in all ſort of Literature: In both theſe Occurrences, we muſt behave our ſelves, <hi>cum ſpecimine ingenii &amp; modeſtiae,</hi> in ſuch a manner as may diſcover in ſome meaſure our Capacity, but withal en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to gain the Hearts of thoſe we ſpeak to, by mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and moderation in our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
               <p>If we are to meet deſignedly in any Aſſembly, for the diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſome Doctrinal Point, 'tis expedient we come not unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd, becauſe if our thoughts be confuſed, our utterance ſhall neither be eaſie nor exact, which could prove ſome diſadvantage to us.</p>
               <p>We muſt take a ſpecial care
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49595:49"/> all the while of our debate to keep our ſelves in a middle tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, becauſe if we be too cold, our imagination ſhall not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us quickly enough with ſuch expreſſions as may be fitteſt in the preſent juncture, and if we are in the other extream, we ſhall utter our ſentiments confuſedly, and ſay many things ſuperfluous; yea, it happens commonly when we are diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd by the immoderate heat of our imagination, that we ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther underſtand not, or miſtake what is ſaid in oppoſition to what we advance, and ſo loſe a conſiderable advantage over our Adverſary by not reflecting where the weak of his diſcourſe lies; we think only on't when the ſhoke is paſt, that we could have eaſily return'd this or that anſwer, and preſs'd our <hi>Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:49595:50"/> with ſuch and ſuch Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Thoſe fiery Diſputants cauſe the By-ſtanders to believe they either miſtruſt their Cauſe or their Wit; as if what they cannot gain by reaſon, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to by a clamorous paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>Here we are to obſerve, if the perſons we diſpute againſt be of greater renown in the World, for their Learning, than we are; we wrong our ſelves, if through meer envy, we oppoſe their Sentiments: We muſt then be ſure we are in the right, before we undertake to contradict ſuch men, and then do it rather as propoſing our doubts, than in an inſulting manner. Yea, my advice to you in this caſe is, If you judge they will be more credited than you, becauſe of their great Authority and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49595:50"/> to yield ſeemingly to their Opinion, though you be ſure they are miſtaken in what they aſſert: For 'tis prudence in ſuch conjunctures, to propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion our behaviour to that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute we have got hitherto in the World, without reſpect to theſe, not ordinary Gifts God has, perhaps, favoured us with.</p>
               <p>There is as yet, a delicate point my Subject engageth me to ſpeak of, if we muſt debate about matters of Religion, and in what manner. I ſay, then generally ſuch diſputes are to be ſhunn'd, becauſe they end alwaies foul and in quarrels, unleſs thoſe we ſpeak to be willing to hear the truth from us, and diſpute rather for <hi>Eſclairciſment</hi> than Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory: but no man is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to diſpute Chriſtian Truths, as the Exiſtency of God,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49595:51"/> his Incarnation, Paſſion, Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe this would be an occaſion of ſcandal to the Hearers, and a weakning of their Faith: On this account the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſt Divines are worthy of blame, who put all our Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to a hard Tryal at the Bench, I may ſo ſay, of Humane Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: One Inſtance will convince you, I wrong them not, they diſpute in their Schools, if there can be any true demonſtration of God's Exiſtency every one pretends to find it out: But I deſire you to obſerve, that what ever one ſaies on this Point is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by another: What is then the concluſion of their Debates? a moſt execrable Blaſphemy, that Atheiſm is a probable Doctrine: This Inference I heard raiſed in a familiar Conference againſt four learned <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> who ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49595:51"/> at the firſt hearing of it, ſtood ſtock-ſtill and anſwered but little to the purpoſe, becauſe the Opponent argued thus, <hi>ad Hominem:</hi> You grant there is no demonſtration of God's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtency which is not probably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by ſome of your Doctors: If then you will ſpeak conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentially to your ſelves you muſt of neceſſity confeſs you have no certainty of his Being, but only a meer probable Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which by your Principles you are not obliged to hold, ſince you teach either part of Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles may be ſecurely embrac'd.</p>
               <p>You ſee what Extreams Men may <hi>ſometimes</hi> thruſt <hi>themſelves</hi> into <hi>through</hi> a too <hi>diſputative</hi> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour: Let us take this <hi>general Rule</hi> when we are engag'd to ſpeak of Matters relating to Religion, to argue alwaies in confirmation of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49595:52"/> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Truths; In order to reſolve theſe groundleſs doubts, our weak reaſon may ſuggeſt to us in oppoſition to them.</p>
               <p>As for the manner of diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in Matters concerning Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, we muſt take our meaſures by the quality of our Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, and force them alwaies to point out to us the Ground they build on: For inſtance, preſs a <hi>Romaniſt</hi> to tell you in what part of Scripture the General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils are declared infallible Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of Controverſies; where they read that the particular Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Univerſal Church; that 'tis lawful to worſhip the Croſs, <hi>cultu latrie,</hi> with that Sovereign Cult due to God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; that there is any other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator we ought to invocate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides our only Mediator Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:49595:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi> Of the Intereſs'd Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</head>
               <p>I Mean by the Intereſs'd Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, that ſort of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe wherein we treat of our own, or our Neighbours Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns: we muſt here take our meaſures from the Nature of the buſineſs we undertake, and change the means we had reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at firſt upon for a good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs according to the variance of emergencies, that may render them unfit for the end we intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them for: I need not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct here <hi>States-men</hi> or <hi>Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors</hi> how to behave themſelves in their reſpective Functions, they are commonly Men of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49595:53"/> eminent parts, and underſtand perfectly how to manage their Maſters concern; their common practice is in Conferences rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to their Princes Intereſt, to follow ſcrupulouſly their inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, ſupplying nevertheleſs ſome things in Occurrencies by their own Prudence, to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, or diſapprov'd of by the Prince as he ſhall think fit. The intereſs'd converſe I ſpeak of here, is that which is moſt ordinary between private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, wherein we muſt aim not ſo much at a vain Repute of Wit, but rather of Chriſtian Wiſdom, as ſhewing our ſelves ready to give every one his due: let us then be real in our intentions, and ſincere in our expreſſions, ſhunning all intermixture of <hi>Amphibologies,</hi> or <hi>Ambiguous Speech,</hi> for we are out of fancy
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49595:53"/> for naked Truth, if once we fall in conceit with Equivocations, and mental Reſervations, which if you are Guilty of, you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be baniſh'd all Civil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, as deſigning to deceive thoſe you deal with. This Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſory practice of Equivocating is ſo cuſtomary to ſome <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> that you can neither tye them by Promiſe, nor by Oath; for if they Promiſe or Swear, 'tis with a mental Preciſion, taking the thing in this ſenſe, not in that you intended, in this reſpect, not in that other, which would put upon them an Obligation of performance: then which the Devil himſelf could invent no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more deſtructive to all the good we may reap by humane Society. If this ſubtile way of Cheating were allowed of, <hi>vere homo homini eſſet Lupus,</hi> one Man
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49595:54"/> would be worſe than a <hi>Woolf</hi> to another, and our condition would be ſafer if we liv'd like Wild Beaſts ſeperated one from another, than 'tis now, if by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving together we may fall a Prey to thoſe who aſſure us moſt of their kindneſs and friendſhip. Come not then to treat with your Friend as a Serpent careſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with the Tail, and killing with a double Tongue: which if once he diſcover, as 'tis eaſie, you make an irrecoverable loſs of his friendſhip, and your own intereſt.</p>
               <p>Whatever I have ſaid hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is to be practiſed, if you have undertaken to treat with others for your Friends Concerns, look upon his Affairs as your own, and go about them with a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diligence, but ſtill without any deſign of impoſing upon thoſe you deal withal: If you
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49595:54"/> are to ask any favour for him or your ſelf, from a perſon that may help your preſent exigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, remember of two things. 1. To chuſe a fit ſeaſon to make your Addreſs, for Men are not apt to be ſpoken to at all hours, and are now in humour to grant what in another time they will refuſe; 'tis then a part of your Prudence to lay hold on the fitteſt occaſion, <hi>captare mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les aditus &amp; mollia fandi tempora,</hi> becauſe 'tis bald, and if you let it ſlip, you ſhall not eaſily catch it again. 2. Think well before you make your Application, for inſtance, to a Prince on the true motives, which may more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly perſwade him, to propoſe them diſtinctly, and in few words, and then withdraw with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out importuning him any more; Tho' ſometimes importunity
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:49595:55"/> may be made uſe of when all other means fail us, becauſe Men will often do what they are not inclin'd to, to be rid of our troubleſome aſſiduities.</p>
               <p>As to the ſeaſonable time of ſpeaking, either in our own or our Friends behalf, 'tis as yet ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſable, and grounded both on reaſon and experience, that the Morning is not ſo fit a time as the Afternoon, becauſe the good temper of our Souls depending wholly on that of our Bodies, we are not ſo well diſpoſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore meat, as after, as the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb</hi> inſinuates, <hi>when I am hungry I am angry,</hi> but our Spirit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reviv'd by a ſubſtantial and plentiful food, we are more chearful and readier to give au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and favours to ſuch as make uſe of this good <hi>Interval,</hi> to require them of us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:49595:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> The Character of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine Humour.</head>
               <p>THoſe we call Sanguine in whom the Blood domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers, they are the fitteſt of all Men for humane Society; ſo as the Body is Dead without Blood, <hi>una eademque via fugiunt ſanguis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que animuſque;</hi> we may likewiſe ſay our Converſation languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and dies, if there be no San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine preſent to revive it: Their Geſts are frequent, but decent, and becoming them well; their looks and their whole Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance inſpire nothing but joy. In the poſture of their Bodies, whether they ſit or ſtand, they uſe their own freedom, and hate
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49595:56"/> extreamly whatever is uneaſie; they are commonly eloquent, and diſcourſe (if they have any tincture of Learning) of every thing with great falicity; they diſtinguiſh themſelves in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation by a certain extempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary quickneſs, which ſurprizeth the duller ſort; an Innocent Railery is their greateſt delight, in which ſometimes they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed. Hence 'tis they content themſelves more ſometimes, than thoſe they converſe withal, who being perhaps, incapable of an anſwer to a witty word, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine to ſee themſelves become a Subject of Sport to the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; nevertheleſs their compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency is ſo exact, that they will put on in an inſtant a ſerious humour, if they think you in the leaſt offended with their mirth, they are pleas'd in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49595:56"/> with whatever you ſay, how great Nonſenſe ſoever it be. If they laugh you ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times out of your Patience, by reaſon of ſome rudeneſs of yours, they are to be pardon'd, becauſe this is an effect of their move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and lively Spirits, which they can hardly command; yet they contain ſometimes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo far as to diſſemble their reſentment, when they are tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to the quick, or turn Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily into a Jeſt, what you have rudely ſaid in ſad Earneſt; they have a ſpecial Talent to add pleaſant Circumſtances to what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they have heard; as alſo to invent in the inſtant, things that never were with ſuch an air of probability, that they are eaſily believ'd by the ſimple ſort, as to all the Circumſtances of their Tales, and by the moſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49595:57"/> knowing, as to the Subſtance. We muſt nevertheleſs pardon them this fault, their aim being no other but to pleaſe which they attain to ſometimes bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by an ingenious fiction, than a naked expoſition of the Truth; they are talkative beyond mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, becauſe they think that whatſoever they ſay pleaſeth others as much as themſelves; they are Naturally inclin'd to Flattery, and the apteſt people of the World to Inchaunt Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; they are extreamly Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemental, and upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count moſt agreeable to Ladies who commonly delight to hear their own praiſes, true or falſe; they never continue any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable time upon the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, but paſs on a ſuddain from one thing to another, becauſe they know ſomewhat of every
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49595:57"/> thing, and few things wholly; they cauſe others often to ſuffer what they are moſt impatient of themſelves, I mean their tedious and endleſs Tales; but becauſe of their eaſie humour, they may be interrupted without offence, but not without incivility; they ſpeak often to their own praiſe, yet with ſuch modeſt Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, and delicacy of expreſſion, that ye would not judge them much concern'd in what they ſay; they are not ſuſpicious, but ready to think and ſpeak good of every one; they love exceſſively their Pleaſures, and diſcourſe willingly of their paſt Debaucheries and new Projects, either of lawful or unlawful di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions; upon the account of their greater eaſe, they chuſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten rather to yield than to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, they become eaſily fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49595:58"/> and make a full acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance at the very firſt meeting, diſcovering to a Stranger as to a concern'd Friend, their Deſigns and Affairs; Truſt them with few Secrets of moment, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of their Spirits, and the Volubility of their Tongues, make them incapable of a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, unleſs they reſiſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; for <hi>ſapiens dominabitur aſtris,</hi> that violent Inclination of theirs, to bring forth inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whatſoever they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:49595:58"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. V.</hi> The Character of the Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick.</head>
               <p>THe Cholerick are not averſe from Humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, but their unruly and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering humour is almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable, they ſeem always to be unſatisfied with whatever you either ſay or do to humour them. If you contradict their ſentiments they will riſe in a fury, and whenſoever you aſſert any thing they think not ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they like it not, they ſhall tell you very civilly, you are groſly miſtaken; or more ſmoothly thus, <hi>Devil a word you ſay, is true:</hi> If ſuch perſons be the Governours of Families,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49595:59"/> their Houſes reſemble Hell, where there is no order, but a perpetual confuſion. You ſhall meet with none that have a greater conceit of themſelves, and ſpeak more in converſing to their own advantage, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract generally of all Mankind; if they cannot blame your action, they will cenſure your intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they ſhall force upon you if they can their ſentiments, and if by reaſon they Maſter you not, they will affright you into their ſide, by Contumelies and flat Injuries; Yet they have ſome good moments, and will make a ſhow of an extraordinary complaiſance to all they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with; but truſt not too much to this Calm, it is like that of the Sea, it will be chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on a ſuddain into a Stormy Paſſion; they think they ſpeak
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49595:59"/> not like Men, unleſs they Swear and Curſe like Devils; and this they will do in cold blood, their cuſtom being now changed into Nature; they ſhall diſcourſe ſo long as you ſeem to Credit them of their great Actions, their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pedigree, their Children, and of whatever may contribute to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the increaſe of that eſteem they are eaſily perſwaded you have for them; in debates of Learning they are commonly overcome by their own fury, which makes them incapable of reflecting on what is ſaid againſte them, and their thoughts cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing forth altogether, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rance is embaraſs'd, and unea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> they are not fit for Embaſſies, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> management of great Affairs, which require a certain mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, they are not capable of; they are rude in their Converſe
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49595:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:49595:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:49595:61"/> with Ladies, they are neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Complemental enough, but after a Martial manner, and far from the ſmoothneſs of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine Temper: the roughneſs of their humour will hinder them to comply with a Ladies ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not only when they have reaſon on their ſide, in which caſe alſo Civility would require our deference to the Sex, but likewiſe when evidently they have it not. Of all Men they are commonly the greateſt Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, and leſs to be truſted too, becauſe their paſſion only prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting them to ſpeak, they are little reflexive on what they ſay; and either promiſe things they are not able to perform, or will not when a more ſober temper hath taken place of their former fit. In Diſputes relating to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be upon your Guards,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49595:61"/> leaſt on a ſuddain they draw up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, for this way of arguing is more ordinary to them, than by reaſon; ſo they never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence the underſtanding to conviction, becauſe they manage not the will by a civil way of debating; as in ſuch conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures they ſpeak much, they ſtagger often from the Center to the Circumference, from Truth to Falſhood, giving a great advantage by their rudeneſs, and precipitation, to a moderate and modeſt Adverſary. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs when they are once ſenſible by experience of their own weakneſs, they will counterfeit a Phlegmatick temper by an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected moderation, which as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forc'd, they put off again at the leaſt occaſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:49595:62"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> The Character of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly Humour.</head>
               <p>WE eſteem thoſe of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly Temper judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and witty, tho' not ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, nor ſo ſharp as the Sanguine. They ſpeak little, but think much and twice, before they ſpeak once: their chief ſtudy is to pronounce Sentences, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend great Senſe in few words: by their very jeſts, ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſmiles, fierce looks, they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their Secret Pride: they generally ſpeak ill of all, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves only excepted, and if Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture has beſtowed upon them any not ordinary Talent, their own Self-conceit as a Magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49595:62"/> Glaſs, will raiſe it to a huge bulk: they think it a Point of Honour not to yield to any Mans ſentiments: they ſtand to their own fancies how ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſoever, with an Obſtinacy equal to that of Hereſie: they miſ-interpret often what is ſaid without deſign, as being beyond expreſſion ſuſpicious to their own perpetual diſturbance: they anſwer ſometimes no otherwiſe than by a diſdainful ſmile, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be that they undervalue what others ſay, or think it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curer for their Repute to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: but this affected ſilence is a too viſible mark of a ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pride: they are ſometimes troubleſome, becauſe of their heavy and ſleepy humour, yet they take often ſuch fits of Mirth, that you would think they have chang'd their Nature:
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49595:63"/> they are not very Complemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, yet Civil enough: they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble Naturally their ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and are capable of a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret: they are complaiſant when they judge their complacency is ſubſervient to their Intereſt: otherwiſe expect ſcarce Juſtice at their hands far, leſs a favour, tho' they could do it at the eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Rate: they ſpeak harſhly to their Servants, to their Equals diſdainfully, with an uneaſie and forc'd reſpect to their Superiors: they pretend to have a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of what is to come, and to judge better of every thing than their Neighbours: they deſire to be harken'd to when they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, as Oracles, and when they are ſilent, they would have you to think they are meditating on great things: their utterance is ſlow and uneaſie, till their ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49595:63"/> be exalted to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of heat, without which we never expreſs our thoughts flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently: they ſpeak ſometimes out of purpoſe, either becauſe they reflect not on what is ſaid, or becauſe they intend to change the Subject, as not agreeable to their preſent Temper: their Diſcourſe is commonly ſenceful enough, but their affected ſilence is often nothing elſe but a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent coverture of their weakneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VII.</hi> The Character of the Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick Humour.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Phlegmaticks</hi> are thoſe the <hi>French</hi> call properly, <hi>Des Apathicks,</hi> without paſſion, or inſenſible not through know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or deſign, but becauſe of their dull Spirits: they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49595:64"/> unconcern'd in Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and ſpeak no otherwiſe than <hi>Machines,</hi> by your moving firſt all ſort of Wheels: I mean by uſing all imaginable Induſtry to engage them once to make the <hi>Ceremony of opening their Mouths,</hi> which they do at length with ſuch an Indetermination, that you muſt determine them again before their lips fall toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: they ſeem to ſpell in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo ſlowly they go on; ſo I may ſay, they both draw and quarter their words. When you have heard the firſt word, you may look about to your Neighbours, or re-collect your ſelf a while, the Gentleman muſt caugh, and ſpit three or four times, e're he utters the ſecond: and then infallibly to gain time, he ſhall ſollicit your Attention, with an often repeated, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49595:64"/> ye Sir, Ye take me Sir:</hi> to make uſe of what we call <hi>Point d'eſprit,</hi> before ſuch men, is a loſs of time, they ſhall ſtand amazed at what you mean, without either applauſe or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: they are not capable of an extemporary diſpute, becauſe their imagination is ever cold, and furniſheth them not with a reply when they are attack'd: Nature has not been intirely a Step-Mother to 'em, if after a long Meditation, they are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſpeak, or write good Senſe: whatever they advance they ſtand to through wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, not throw judgment: if you ask them a reaſon for what they do, they have ſo much Wit as to tell you <hi>'tis their will,</hi> and nothing elſe: they love not Converſation, not that they paſs their time when alone, in Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49595:65"/> as the thinking ſort of Men do, but meerly becauſe they are ſo more at their eaſe, as thinking on juſt nothing: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they delight ſo much in the ſolitude, they are to the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher,</hi> either Gods, or which I am more apt to believe, down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Beaſts: yet they appear Men again, and ſpeak pertinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for their own Concerns, and can inform you of Twenty Arts how to gain and ſpare a Peny: for as they are ordinarily in a furious conceit of that ſhining Earth we call Gold and Silver, ſo they love to ſpeak of it: you need neither ſhow your anger againſt this ſort of people, nor uſe them at the Complemental Mode, you ſhall find them as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd with your Wrath, as inſenſible to your Civility: yet they are rather not civil, than
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:49595:65"/> poſitively incivil: they ſpend a conſiderable time and many words, to ſay but little, they ſpeak to Ladies rather with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reſpect, than a true diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect: they kill their Inferiors and Equals, with old and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Stories, but ſay nothing in preſence of their Superiours, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a meer <hi>yes Sir, or no Madam,</hi> their longeſt Anſwers to every Queſtion: they endeavour ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to rouſe up their Spirits with a higher tone, rather than a true anger, which falls imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately with the fall of their voice: if they have a true love for their Children, 'tis like that of irrational Creatures, they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver tell them of it, though they make them ſenſible enough of the reality of their Affections, by procuring them all Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:49595:66"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VIII.</hi> The Character of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> as to their way of converſing.</head>
               <p>THogh the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have been accounted from all times, one of the moſt polite Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> yet I am ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded they have ſo far improved themſelves in the Art of all civil Converſe, ſince His Majeſties Happy reſtoration, that if we compare them now, to what formerly they were, we ſhall have reaſon to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how ſo a great change to the better could happen in ſo ſhort a time: their former ſtiff form of converſing, is now changed into a free, brisk, and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:49595:66"/> lively air, which is the very Life of Converſation; And as in their Method of Divine Worſhip, they have ſhunn'd the extreams, neith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er rejecting all Ceremonies, as ſome of their Neighbours do, nor admitting too many, as thoſe of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> perſwaſion: ſo likewiſe in their way of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, they hold a juſt middle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween an exceſſive <hi>Gayete,</hi> and too affected Gravity: their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe becauſe of this good tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is commonly to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and ſenſeful enough: they are not ſo familiar at firſt with Strangers, as the <hi>Scotch</hi> or the <hi>French;</hi> yet you ſhall find no where ſo real, and more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Friends, if once you are poſſeſs'd of their Friendſhip: they ſtand to their ſentiments if oppoſed, yet without Obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, chuſing rather to yield to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:49595:67"/> reaſon, than overcome by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: they keep great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures with their very Friends, and are ſcarce ever guilty of too great familiarity: they diſcover their Secrets to few, hardly to thoſe of their greateſt intimacy: they commend highly, and I confeſs deſervedly too, their own Nation, but they underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue ſometimes without reaſon, ſome Neighbouring Nations, yet this is the defect but of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle number, and of thoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly who have never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd Strangers, nor ſtirr'd from home: they expreſs themſelves upon any Subject with a greater ſhow of Natural Eloquence, than any other Nation of <hi>Europe,</hi> though commonly they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted better <hi>Writers,</hi> than <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> perhaps becauſe of the want of that great Action in
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49595:67"/> their Pulpits, which we obſerve in the Preachers of all other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: they can digeſt a Railery from a Friend, but hardly if it come from a Stranger: as they are hardy and reſolute in all their undertakings, ſo they are in their words, diſcovering their Contempt of their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, rather than fear: they are exactly Complaiſant to the weaker Sex, and with greater deference in every particular, than any other Nation of the World: On this account I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe 'tis become Proverbial, <hi>That</hi> England <hi>is the Hell of Horſes, and the Paradice of Women,</hi> which is moſt true, if Liberty and Freedom to do what they liſt, be the true Prerogatives of Paradice: Strangers muſt not judge of this Nation by ſome of the common ſort, whoſe
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49595:68"/> rudeneſs they complain of at their firſt arrival: the Commons in <hi>England</hi> generally as well as the Gentlemen, are both Civil, Judicious, and Witty, beyond thoſe of other Nations; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſpeak commonly to their Superiours of what degree ſo ever, or Character, with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectuous freedom, to few fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly, to their Equals and Friends too, unconcernedly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier to ſerve them when need requires, than to feed their hopes with large promiſes; yet they are of late become as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemental, as any other Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Nation, which whether it be a Vice or a Virtue, I ſhall not determine. Their converſe with thoſe they are unacquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with, is ſomewhat cold and ſerious, miſtruſting Prudently whom they know not: they
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49595:68"/> will diſcourſe a Point of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Philoſophy, with ſuch Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and Sharpneſs, with ſuch an air of probability, that you cannot oppoſe their ſentiments upon the account of any viſible untruth they advance: they have improved, and improve dayly themſelvs in this noble Science to that degree of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, no other Nation had reach'd to in the foregoing Ages. The Right Honourable <hi>Rob. Boyle,</hi> is Renowned all <hi>Europe</hi> over, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of his Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Philoſophy, he is a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of extraordinary parts, and deſerves well the Repute, he has got now every where, both abroad and at home, of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Philoſopher. I ſhall ſay nothing here of the <hi>Scotch,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their way of converſe is not much different from that
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:49595:69"/> of the <hi>French,</hi> their humours meeting with ſomewhat of <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy;</hi> I add only their Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Gentry may compare, to ſay no more, with any Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Europe,</hi> as to Courage, Wit, Sharpneſs, and Civility.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IX.</hi> The Character of the <hi>French,</hi> as to their way of <hi>Converſing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>French</hi> are Naturally Civil, and Complaiſant indifferently to all: they are talkative beyond meaſure in Converſation, and ſometimes after a long diſcourſe they have ſaid but little, their eaſie utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and the quickneſs of their, imagination engaging them of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:49595:69"/> in Tautologies, ſo much hated by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that they ſcarce ever make uſe of <hi>Synonima's,</hi> or idle <hi>Repetitions,</hi> they love Railery, and underſtand it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than any other Nation of <hi>Europe,</hi> their Mirth is innocent, and their Jeſts without offence: they Honour Men of great parts whatever Nation they be of: they are extreamly kind to Strangers, and on this account will favour them in all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they hate no Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nation; but whom they fear moſt, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> they moſt eſteem: they were ſo far from being jealous of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the <hi>Engliſh</hi> obtain'd by theſe incomparable Actions of Valour they did in their late Wars againſt the <hi>Germans,</hi> that they contributed not a little to the encreaſe thereof, by publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:49595:70"/> them in their <hi>Gazettes</hi> with due <hi>Elogiums,</hi> and the moſt material Circumſtances: If they talk too much to the commendation of their own Nation, you may eaſily par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them on this account, That they ſpeak but little to the diſadvantage of other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſeem to admire whatever comes from abroad; You may obſerve in their Speech, and all their Actions, a certain confidence ſo neſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to all Gentlemen, that whatever may be their other Endowments, without this they cannot be accounted well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred: they ſpeak to their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals almoſt with the ſame reſpect they do to their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours: 'tis obſervable the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of quality every where, but in <hi>France</hi> particularly, are
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:49595:70"/> far beyond the reſt in Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: the <hi>French</hi> in their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar converſe, will ſometimes talk at random againſt their own Prince, and his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but if a Stranger whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers any thing to his diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, they ſhall oppoſe him vigorouſly, as loving ſtill (how rudely ſoever dealt withal) their Prince, and glorying in his greatneſs.</p>
               <p>I know no People in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> ſharper in their Repar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees than the <hi>French,</hi> yet they play often upon words, and delight in Childiſh Alluſions. Their Language is polite e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, but not ſo copious as the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> they will ſpare no pains to teach a Stranger their pronounciation, but you muſt give them leave to ſport and laugh, if you pronounce
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:49595:71"/> amiſs: this is the only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they pretend to for the trouble they are at: they are extreamly Complemental, not ſo much by Art as by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and thoſe amongſt them that have no tincture of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, know yet ſo much of Humanity, as to pay you the Homage of their hearty thanks for a good turn done in good and ſenceful Terms. As ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary <hi>Careſſes</hi> cover ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Cheat, or a deſign to Cheat, truſt not too much to their Complements, they turn ſtill by ſome reflex or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to their own intereſt: the <hi>French</hi> Ladies are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly well-bred, and behave themſelves in a familiar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with a certain <hi>Bone-Grace,</hi> holding more of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture than Art, their expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:49595:71"/> are graceful, neat, and ſmooth, their Countenance en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened with the Beams of joy and contentedneſs, their Air, their Geſts, and the whole poſture of their Body, natural and eaſie, their <hi>Cercles</hi> are the beſt Schools of the <hi>French Politeſs:</hi> the <hi>French</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally diſcourſe fluently up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Subject whatſoever, with an accuracy ſufficient in a familiar converſe, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little of every thing, and few things to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, or intirely: they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in this Age, a certain cold temper, and moderation in all their words, and Actions, and think they give no ſmall praiſe to a Man when they have ſaid, <hi>C'eſt un home qui a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aucoup de ſang froid,</hi> He is a Man that has much cold Blood:
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:49595:72"/> you have all freedom to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their ſentiments in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, but becauſe they take it for no leſs diſhonour to be over-power'd by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon than by the Sword, you may expect a vigorous reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, they will oppoſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to Reaſon, and if they find themſelves worſted, they know how to ridicule the Matter and turn it into a Jeſt, that ſo they may divert the By-ſtanders from reflecting on their weakneſs, and your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49595:72"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
